<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<chapter xml:id="intro"
      xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      version="5.0" xml:lang="en">

  <title>Introduction</title>
  <para>
    Today mobile applications retrieve asynchronously information from multiple sites.
    Developers have two ways to get this information:
  </para>
  <para>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        Poll: Periodically query for information from the server.
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        Push: The server sends the information to the client when the required
        information is available.
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </para>
  <para>
    The first method is strongly discouraged due to the large number of connections
    made to the server needlessly, because information is not available and you lose time and resources.
  </para>
  <para>
    That is why the PUSH methods are widely used for information retrieval,
    anyway how PUSH platforms are currently working are misusing mobile radio
    resources and also consuming too much battery.
  </para>
  <para>
    This article aims to explain how to manage this kind of messaging, problems
    with existing solutions and finally how Telefónica Digital, within the framework
    of the development of Firefox OS operating system, defined a new solution which is
    friendlier to the network and uses lower battery consumption on mobile devices.
  </para>

  <section>
    <title>State of the art</title>
    <para>
      Historically, mobile operators offered (and offer) real mechanisms for PUSH notifications,
      also known as WAP PUSH. WAP PUSH can "wake up" applications when any action
      is required from them by the server side (without interaction from the user).
      Sending WAP PUSH messages is done in the circuit-switching domain, the same used
      for voice and SMS, and that is why the user don't need to establish a data connection.
      These kind messages work properly out of the box.
    </para>
    <para>
      WAP PUSH solutions works great when the user is registered in the mobile network,
      but if you are out of coverage or connected to a WiFi hotspot instead a celular
      network, you can not receive these messages.
    </para>
    <para>
      Also, if we add that this messages implies an economic cost (basically it
      is a short message SMS) the effect is that major smartphone operating systems
      (Apple iOS and Google Android) have implemented a parallel solution that would
      work regardless of the mobile network to which the user belongs and it can
      run smoothly when they are using WiFi networks.
    </para>

    <section>
      <title>Current Internet solutions issues</title>
      <para>
        Internet PUSH solutions are based on a public accesible server which handles
        all the notification delivery.
      </para>
      <para>
        These solutions were designed without considering the mobile networks
        way of working and forces the handset to maintain an open socket with
        the server in order to avoid misnotifications.
      </para>
      <para>
        This way of working increases the signalling and the handsets battery
        consume.
        For more information about this, please refer to the
        "<xref linkend="network_issues" endterm="network_issues_title" />" chapter
      </para>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Service Description</title>
    <para>
      The Notification Server platform is aimed to deliver push notifications
      (small messages like a real-time chat, a JSON data structure defining
      the goal of a soccer match) to web based terminals inside mobile networks.
    </para>
    <para>
      The main objective of this service is to deliver these messages
      considering the way of working of the mobile radio so the battery
      consumption and traffic generated is reduced to the minimal.
      It is developed for working on stable Internet connections, like on
      Wi-Fi or Ethernet.
    </para>
  </section>
</chapter>
