<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<chapter xml:id="network_issues"
      xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
      version="5.0" xml:lang="en">

  <title xml:id="network_issues_title">Mobile network issues with current PUSH platforms</title>
  <para>
    This chapter explains why current solutions are bad for the mobile networks
    and how we designed this server to solve this issues.
  </para>
  <para>
    In order to understand the complete problem, we need to introduce you on how
    the mobile nerworks work at radio level and also how the carriers have their
    network infrastructure. So, go ahead !
  </para>

  <section>
    <title>Mobile networks in a Private or Public LAN</title>
    <para>
      Since on IPv4 the amount of free adresses is really low, celular networks
      were divided into the ones with real IPv4 adresses (normally for 3G modems)
      and private adressing model for handsets.
    </para>
    <para>
      On the case of private networks, it's obvious that it's not possible to
      directly notify the handset when the server has a notification for it, so
      smartphone manufacturers decided to maintain opened channels with their
      servers so it's possible to notify handsets asynchronously.
    </para>
    <para>
      On the other hand, if the handset has a public address, or is using IPv6,
      it's teorically possible to send the message directly making third party
      solutions unuseful, however in order to protect users, carriers can deploy
      firewalls to avoid direct access from Internet to the handset.
    </para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Mobile Network. Circuit domain states</title>
    <para>
      In the 3GPP TS 25.331 specification, we can query all the circuit domain
      statues of the RRC Layer (Radio Resource Control).
    </para>
    <para>
      In order to simplify, we only list the third generation (3G) states:
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          Cell_DCH (Dedicated Channel)
          <para>
            When the handset is in this state is because it has a dedicated
            channel on the mobile network.
          </para>
          <para>
            Normally the network sets a handsent into this state when it's
            transmitting a big amount of data.
          </para>
          <para>
            The inactivity time of this state is really short, known as T1 timer
            it should vary between 5 and 20 seconds. If T1 is fired, the handset
            will be changed to the Cell_FACH state.
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          Cell_FACH
          <para>
            In this state the handset is connected to the mobile network using
            a shared channel with other handsets.
          </para>
          <para>
            Normally, this state is assigned by the network when the handset is
            transmitting a small amount of data.
            So it's common to use it when sending keep-alive packages.
          </para>
          <para>
            The inactivity time of this state is a little longer (30 seconds) and
            is konwn as T2 timer. When T2 timer is shotted, the handset will be
            moved to Cell_PCH or URA_PCH (depending on the type of network)
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          Cell_PCH or URA_PCH (PCH: Paging Channel) (URA: UTRAN Registration Area)
          <para>
            In this state the handset is not able to send any data except
            signalling information in order to be able to localize the handset
            inside the celullar network.
          </para>
          <para>
            In both states, the RRC connection is established and open, but it's
            rarely used.
          </para>
          <para>
            In this state, the handset informs the network every time the device
            change from one sector to another so the network is able to known
            exactly the BTS which is offering service to the device.
          </para>
          <para>
            The T3 timer defines the maximum time to be in a PCH state. This timer
            is longer than T1 and T2 and depends on each carrier. When it's fired
            the handset is moved to IDLE mode so if new data transmission is needed
            the handset will need near 2 seconds to restablish the channel and a
            lot of signalling messages.
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          RRC_IDLE
          <para>
            This is the most economical state since the handset radio is practically
            stopped.
          </para>
          <para>
            In this state, the radio is only listening to radio messages quering
            the handset to "Wake Up" (paging messages).
          </para>
          <para>
            Also, the handset modem is listening the cell data so each time it
            detects that the user changed from one LAC (Localization Area Code -
            Group of multiple BTS) to another, the handset will change to the
            PCH state in order to inform the network.
          </para>
          <para>
            So when a handset is in this state, it can be Waked Up to a more
            active state and also the network knowns the LAC where the handset
            is moving, so if the network needs to inform the handset it should
            send a broadcast paging message through all the LAC BTS in order to
            locate the handset.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </para>
    <para>
      The following scheme represent the different radio states ordered by
      power comsuption on the device:
    </para>
    <para>
      <imagedata fileref="resources/rcc_states.png" align="center" width="5in" />
    </para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Mobile Network. Package domain states</title>
    <para>
      In the 3GPP TS 23.060 specification, we can analyse all the package domain
      states of the GMM Layer (GPRS Mobility Management).
    </para>
    <para>
      The package domain states are simpler than radio ones (only 3 states):
    </para>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        READY (2G) / PMM_CONNECTED (3G)
        <para>
          The handset has a PDP context established and is able to send and
          receive data.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        STANDBY (2G) / PMM_IDLE (3G)
        <para>
          The handset isn't transmitting anything but the PDP context is not
          closed, so it maintains a valid IP address.
        </para>
        <para>
          In this state the handset don't consume any resource but the network is
          maintaining his IP address as a valid one, so it's very important to try
          to maintain the handset in this state in order to be able to Wake Up
          it and change to a PMM_CONNECTED state in order to transmit/receive
          information.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        IDLE (2G) / PMM_DETACHED (3G)
        <para>
          In this state, the handset hasn't a PDP context established so it hasn't
          a valid IP address.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Mobile Network. States relation</title>
    <para>
      In this section we show the relation between RRC and GMM states.
    </para>
    <para>
      In order to simplify this table, we only consider the handset is only using
      data channels, so no voice nor SMS (circuit domain) is being used.
    </para>
    <table frame='all'>
      <title>RCC - GMM relation</title>
      <tgroup cols='3' align='left' colsep='1' rowsep='1'>
        <colspec colname='RCC'/>
        <colspec colname='GMM'/>
        <colspec colname='Desc'/>
        <thead>
          <row>
            <entry>RCC State</entry>
            <entry>GMM State (2G/3G)</entry>
            <entry>Description</entry>
          </row>
        </thead>
        <tfoot>
          <row>
            <entry>RCC State</entry>
            <entry>GMM State (2G/3G)</entry>
            <entry>Description</entry>
          </row>
        </tfoot>
        <tbody>
          <row>
            <entry>Cell_DCH</entry>
            <entry>READY/PMM_CONNECTED</entry>
            <entry>
              <para>
                The handset is transmiting or receiving data information using a
                dedicated channel or a HSPA shared channel.
              </para>
            </entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>Cell_FACH</entry>
            <entry>READY/PMM_CONNECTED</entry>
            <entry>
              <para>
                The handset had been transmiting or receiving data some seconds ago
                and due to inactivity had been moved to the Cell_FACH RCC state.
              </para>
              <para>
                Also it's possible that the handset is transmiting or receiving
                small amount of data like pings, keep-alives, cell updates,...
              </para>
            </entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>Cell_PCH/URA_PCH</entry>
            <entry>READY/PMM_CONNECTED</entry>
            <entry>
              <para>
                The handset had been in Cell_FACH some seconds ago and due to
                inactivity had been moved to this less resource consume state.
              </para>
              <para>
                However, the signalling channel is available and is able to change
                to a data transmission state like FACH or DCH with a little amount
                of signalling.
              </para>
            </entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>Cell_PCH/URA_PCH</entry>
            <entry>STANDBY/PMM_IDLE</entry>
            <entry>
              <para>
                The handset is not transmiting nor receiving any amount of data
                and also the signalling connection is closed.
              </para>
              <para>
                However the IP address is maintained by the network and associated
                to this handset.
              </para>
              <para>
                This is one of the most interesting states since the PDP context
                is not closed, the IP address is still valid and the handset is
                not consuming baterry, network traffic,...
              </para>
              <para>
                As soon as the handset needs to restablish the data channel the
                radio state will be changed to FACH or DCH.
              </para>
            </entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>RRC_IDLE</entry>
            <entry>STANDBY/PMM_IDLE</entry>
            <entry>
              <para>
                This state is the same as the previous one since the radio state
                is IDLE.
              </para>
            </entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>RRC_IDLE</entry>
            <entry>IDLE/PMM_DETACHED</entry>
            <entry>
              <para>
                The handset is not transmitting nor receiving anything and also it
                hasn't any PDP context established, so no IP address is available
                for this handset.
              </para>
              <para>
                Normally this state is after 24h of innactivity in the package
                domain.
              </para>
            </entry>
          </row>
        </tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </table>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Mobile Network. Signalling storms</title>
    <para>
      This is a carrier well-know effect after the big adoption of smartphones
      around the word.
    </para>
    <para>
      As we explained in previous sections, each time the network decides to
      move a handset from one state to another is needed to restablish channels
      and starts a negotiation between the network and the handset with the
      signalling protocol.
    </para>
    <para>
      Since nowadays handsets are sending keep-alives to maintain their connections
      opened, the efect is that the handsets is continously changing from one
      state to another producing a lot of signalling in the network and also
      consumes a lot of battery resources.
    </para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Mobile Network. Battery comsuption</title>
    <para>
      The battery comsuption depends on the Radio state. The following list
      represent the amount of battery needed on each state represented in
      relative units:
    </para>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>RRC IDLE: 1 relative unit</listitem>
      <listitem>Cell_PCH: &lt; 2 relative unit</listitem>
      <listitem>URA_PCH: &lt; or equal than Cell_PCH</listitem>
      <listitem>Cell_FACH: 40 relative units</listitem>
      <listitem>Cell_DCH: 100 relative units</listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </section>
</chapter>
