<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<section xml:id="api_internal"
      xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
      version="5.0" xml:lang="es">

  <title>API between the User Agent and the Notification Server</title>
  <para>
    With this API the client device is able to register his applications and
    itself into the selected notification server.
  </para>
  <para>
    This API isn't yet standarised, anyway the one explained here is an 
    on working proposal.
  </para>
  <para>
    The UA-NS API is divided in two transport protocols:
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        POST API: Through the HTTP POST transport protocol the NS will deliver
        valid UATokens to the device.
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        WebSocket API: This is the most important one since all the
        communications (except to recover tokens) with the NS SHALL be driven
        through this API.
        <para>
          On future releases will be supported another channels as Long-Polling
          solutions in order to cover devices which don't support Web Sockets.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <section>
      <title>HTTP POST API</title>
      <para>
        This channel only offers one method to get a valid UAToken.
      </para>
      <section>
        <title>GET UA TOKEN</title>
        <para>
          This method SHOULD be protected to avoid DoS attacks getting millions of
          valid tokens, in any case, this is out of the scope of this protocol.
        </para>
        <para>
          The TOKEN method is called with a simple URL:
          <code>https://&lt;notification_server_base_URL&gt;/token</code>
        </para>
        <para>
          The server will respond with an AES encrypted valid token.
          This token SHALL be used to identify the device in future connections.
        </para>
      </section>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>WebSocket API</title>
      <para>
        Through this channel the device will register itself, his applications,
        and also will be used to deliver PUSH notifications
      </para>
      <para>
        All methods sent through this channel will have the same JSON structure:
      </para>
      <programlisting language="javascript">
      <![CDATA[
      {
        messageType: "<type of message>",
        ... other data ...
      }
      ]]>
      </programlisting>
      <para>
        In which messageType defines one of these commands:
      </para>
      <section>
        <title>registerUA</title>
        <para>
          With this method the device is able to register itself.
        </para>
        <para>
          When a device is registering to a notification server, it SHALL send
          his own valid UAToken and also the device can send additional information
          that can be used to optimize the way the messages will be delivered
          to this device.
        </para>
        <programlisting language="javascript">
        <![CDATA[
        {
          messageType: "registerUA",
          data: {
            uatoken: "<a valid UAToken>",
            interface: {
              ip: "<current device IP address>",
              port: "<TCP or UDP port in which the device is waiting for wake up notifications>"
            },
            mobilenetwork: {
              mcc: "<Mobile Country Code>",
              mnc: "<Mobile Network Code>"
            }
          }
        }
        ]]>
        </programlisting>
        <para>
          The interface and mobilenetwork optional data will be used by the server
          to identify if it has the required infrastructure into the user's mobile
          network in order to send wakeup messages to the IP and port indicated
          in the interface data so it's able to close the WebSocket channel to reduce
          signalling and battery consume.
        </para>
        <para>
          The server response can be:
          <programlisting language="javascript">
          <![CDATA[
          {
            status: "REGISTERED",
            statusCode: 200,
            messageType: "registerUA"
          }
          ]]>
          </programlisting>
          <programlisting language="javascript">
          <![CDATA[
          {
            status: "ERROR",
            statusCode: 40x,
            reason: "Data received is not a valid JSON package",
            messageType: "registerUA"
          }
          ]]>
          </programlisting>
          <programlisting language="javascript">
          <![CDATA[
          {
            status: "ERROR",
            statusCode: 40x,
            reason: "Token is not valid for this server",
            messageType: "registerUA"
          }
          ]]>
          </programlisting>
          <programlisting language="javascript">
          <![CDATA[
          {
            status: "ERROR",
            statusCode: 40x,
            reason: "...",
            messageType: "registerUA"
          }
          ]]>
          </programlisting>
        </para>
      </section>
      <section>
        <title>registerWA</title>
        <para>
          This method is used to register installed applications on the device.
          This shall be send to the notification server after a valid UA registration.
        </para>
        <para>
          Normally, this method will be used each time an application requires a
          new push notification URL (through the WA-UA API) or also each time the
          device is powered on and is re-registering previously registered applications.
        </para>
        <para>
          The required data for application registration is the WAToken and the
          public key.
        </para>
        <programlisting language="javascript">
        <![CDATA[
        {
          messageType: "registerWA",
          data: {
            uatoken: "<a valid UAToken>",
            watoken: "<the WAToken>",
            pbkbase64: "<BASE64 coded public key>"
          }
        }
        ]]>
        </programlisting>
        <para>
          The server response can be:
          <programlisting language="javascript">
          <![CDATA[
          {
            status: "REGISTERED",
            statusCode: 200,
            url: "<publicURL required to send notifications>",
            messageType: "registerUA"
          }
          ]]>
          </programlisting>
          <programlisting language="javascript">
          <![CDATA[
          {
            status: "ERROR",
            statusCode: 40x,
            reason: "...",
            messageType: "registerWA"
          }
          ]]>
          </programlisting>
        </para>
        <para>
          The device service should redirect the received URL to the correct
          application.
        </para>
      </section>
      <section>
        <title>getAllMessages</title>
        <para>
          This method is used to retrieve all pending messages for one device.
        </para>
        <para>
          This will be used each time the device is Waked Up, so it's polling
          pending messages.
        </para>
        <programlisting language="javascript">
        <![CDATA[
        {
          messageType: "getAllMessages",
          data: {
            uatoken: "<a valid UAToken>"
          }
        }
        ]]>
        </programlisting>
        <para>
          The server response can be:
          <programlisting language="javascript">
          <![CDATA[
          {
            messageType: "getAllMessages",
            [
              <Array of notifications with the same format
               as defined in the notification method>
            ]
          }
          ]]>
          </programlisting>
        </para>
      </section>
      <section>
        <title>notification</title>
        <para>
          This message will be used by the server to inform about new notification
          to the device.
        </para>
        <para>
          All recieved notification will have this structure:
        </para>
        <programlisting language="javascript">
        <![CDATA[
        {
          messageType: "notification",
          id: "<ID used by the Application Server>",
          message: "<Message payload>",
          timestamp: "<Since EPOCH Time>",
          priority: "<prio>",
          messageId: "<ID of the message>",
          url: "<publicURL which identifies the final application>"
        }
        ]]>
        </programlisting>
      </section>
      <section>
        <title>ack</title>
        <para>
          For each received notification through notification or getAllMessages,
          the server SHOULD be notified in order to free resources related to
          this notifications.
        </para>
        <para>
          This message is used to acknoledge the message reception.
        </para>
          <programlisting language="javascript">
          <![CDATA[
          {
            messageType: "ack",
            messageId: "<ID of the received message>"
          }
          ]]>
          </programlisting>
      </section>
    </section>
  </para>
</section>
