<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<section xml:id="api_tokens"
      xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
      version="5.0" xml:lang="es">

  <title>Tokens</title>
  <para>
    The tokens are an important part of this API since it identifies each
    (user) actor (device and applications) in a unique or shared way.
  </para>
  <section>
    <title>WAToken</title>
    <para>
      This token identifies the user or group of users and SHALL be a secret.
    </para>
    <para>
      If this token is UNIQUE (and secret, of coures) will identify a unique
      instance of the application related (normally) to one user. In this case
      the returned URL will be unique for this WAToken.
    </para>
    <para>
      If this token is shared by different devices of the SAME user (and secret),
      will identify a unique user with multiple devices. In this case, the returned
      URL will be unique per user but each URL will identify multiple devices
      the user is using.
    </para>
    <example>
      <title>Multiple device messages</title>
      <para>
        This can be used by applications in which the user require the same
        information across his devices, like the mobile and the desktop app.
        Can be used, for example, by e-mail clients.
      </para>
    </example>
    <para>
      Finally, if a developer decides to deliver the same WAToken to all his users
      (in this cases is obviously not a secret one), then the returned URL will
      identify all instances of the same application. In this case each notification
      received in the publicURL will be delivered to ALL the devices which have
      the application installed (and registered). This will be a BROADCAST message.
    </para>
    <example>
      <title>Message broadcast</title>
      <para>
        This can be used by applications in which all users require exactly the
        same information at the same time, like weather applications, latest news, ...
      </para>
    </example>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>UAToken</title>
    <para>
      This token identifies each customer device in a unique way.
    </para>
    <para>
      This token is also used as an identification key since this isn't a random
      one. This token is an AES encrypted string which will be checked for
      validaty each time it's used.
    </para>
    <para>
      This token should be delivered after identify the user in a valid way,
      anyway this identification procedure is out of the scope of this specification.
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>AppToken</title>
    <para>
      Automatic generated token by the notification server which identifies the
      application + user as in a unique fashion.
    </para>
    <para>
      This token is included in the publicURL which identifies the application,
      and normally is a SHA256 hashed string with the WATokent + the Public Key.
    </para>
  </section>
</section>
